<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Css | Getting accountable]]></title>
  <link href="http://jcollado.github.io/blog/blog/categories/css/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jcollado.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-20T01:11:42+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jcollado.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Javier Collado]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinkful FEWD]]></title>
    <link href="http://jcollado.github.io/blog/blog/2013/12/19/thinkful-fewd/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T19:57:21+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jcollado.github.io/blog/blog/2013/12/19/thinkful-fewd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Introduction</h1>

<p>This week I&rsquo;ve completed the FEWD (Front End Web Development) course at
<a href="http://www.thinkful.com">Thinkful</a>. It&rsquo;s been three months of hard work in
which I think I&rsquo;ve made good progress in sharpening my web development skills.
In this post I&rsquo;m sharing my impressions, for those who want to have the opinion
about the course of a former student before making the decision to take it.</p>

<h1>Who is this course for?</h1>

<p>This is a course that can be taken by absolute beginners to learn html, css and
javascript from the ground up, but it&rsquo;s also useful to people who, like me,
already have some experience, but want to improve in any of the technologies
involved.</p>

<h1>What does the course include?</h1>

<p>The resources available to you as a student are:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>curriculum: the course content itself. It&rsquo;s made from content already
available on the internet for free, but structured to introduce new concepts
progressively. It also includes a set of assignments to ensure student
comprehension that have to be posted to the community for feedback (see
below).</p></li>
<li><p>mentoring sessions: every student has half an hour weekly meetings with a
mentor that will provide guidance and specific advice in any area the student
is interested in. This is good not only to get personalized information about
problems, but also because of the accountability that is generated when you commit
to finish some assignment for the following week.</p></li>
<li><p>community: this where you meet other mentors and students like. This is where
you post the work on the assignments to gather feedback aside from the one
provided by your mentor. If you&rsquo;re in trouble this is a good place to ask
because you&rsquo;ll get faster feedback than if you wait for your mentoring
session. Also, if you help other students, it&rsquo;s a nice mechanism to reinforce
your own learning since you&rsquo;ll need to take a look at the same kind of
problem multiple times.</p></li>
<li><p>office hours: these are daily meetings in which you can also ask a mentor
face to face about problems you might have and learn from the questions from
others. As for now, the time isn&rsquo;t very convenient unless you&rsquo;re in the US,
but still it&rsquo;s a good experience to attend them.</p></li>
</ul>


<h1>What assignments will I work on?</h1>

<p>In case you&rsquo;re curious, the assignments that you&rsquo;ll need to work on are
(including links to my personal work):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io/GoogleClone">Google clone</a>: reproduce the Google
homepage.</li>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io/37signalsClone">37signals clone</a>: reproduce the
37signals homepage.</li>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io/HotOrCold">Hot or cold</a>: Number guessing game.</li>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io/ShoppingList">Shopping list</a>: Todo list
application.</li>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io/QuizKnockout">Quiz</a>: Quiz application.</li>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io/DoIt">API hack</a>: An application that takes
advantage of public API.</li>
<li><a href="http://jcollado.github.io">Portfolio</a>: Final project to showcase the work
done during the course.</li>
</ul>


<h1>What will I learn?</h1>

<p>This almost entirely up to you. The more you involve in the community and the
more you work in the assignments, the more advanced stuff you&rsquo;ll get from the
course. Of course, you can get by with just basic html, css and javascript with
jquery; but if you&rsquo;re curious you can much further than that.</p>

<p>In my case, some of the things that I learned are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Object oriented javascript</li>
<li>MVC frameworks</li>
<li>Data binding libraries</li>
<li>Template libraries</li>
<li>CSS preprocessors</li>
<li>Single page applications</li>
<li>Responsive design</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m not an expert in any of the above, but now I&rsquo;m confident that I can refer
to the documentation of any library and/or framework in the future and get up
to speed quickly if I need to.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>After three months of work, I&rsquo;ve learned quite a few interesting things and
I&rsquo;ve got a <a href="http://jcollado.github.io">portolio</a> in which I can work on to
improve in the future which I think is a quite good outcome for the time spent.</p>

<p>What makes the course shine, in my opinion, is that it includes weekly meetings
with a mentor and access to a community of students that are going through the
same problems as you are. This is really powerful to create accountability and
get rid of procrastination to make progress in short time.</p>

<p>In case you&rsquo;re wondering, I feel that I could have learned the same stuff on my
own, but I don&rsquo;t how long would that have taken me. If you&rsquo;re really good in
setting your own goals and keeping the motivation to accomplish them and you&rsquo;ve
got plenty of time to look for good learning resources, then you might not need
the course, but I&rsquo;d still encourage you to think about taking it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
